Guide to the Pen & Pixel Graphics, Inc. Records
University of Houston Libraries
Pen & Pixel Graphics, Inc. Records
1993-2002
06/2010-017
Pen & Pixel Graphics, Inc.
4.50 linear feet
67 digital files (90.3 MB)
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection documents the creative process of Pen & Pixel Graphics, Inc. as it produced album artwork for Houston-area and other American hip hop artists.
Historical Note:
Pen & Pixel Graphics, Inc. was founded in September 1992 by brothers Shawn and Aaron Brauch in Houston, TX. The Brauch brothers got their start in the music business by working for Rap-A-Lot Records in Houston before recognizing that demand for their graphic design work was high enough for them to start their own company.
Pen & Pixel was innovative in its wide use of Photoshop to create CD covers filled with layers of special effects, highly stylized lettering, and plenty of “bling” (flashy jewelry, expensive clothes, luxury cars, and piles of cash). The company became associated mainly with rap and hip hop musicians in the 1990s, working with renowned artists such as Master P and Lil Wayne and record labels such as No Limit Records and Cash Money Records.
In addition to CD covers, Pen & Pixel also produced artwork for posters, logos, and videos.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Digital images; Posters
Topical Term:
Hip-hop -- United States -- History; Hip-hop -- United States -- Pictorial works; Rap (Music) -- Texas -- Houston
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Related Materials:
Pen & Pixel digital collection (http://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/pixel)
Physical Characteristics or Technical Requirements:
Some digital files can be viewed in the UH Digital Library at http://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/pixel. Digital archival materials can also be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room by advance request. Materials not in the Digital Library may require up to one week to access. Contact curator Julie Grob (jgrob@uh.edu) for more information.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the creative process of Pen & Pixel Graphics, Inc. as it produced album artwork for Houston-area and other American hip hop artists. The collection contains 67 digital files, 13 posters, 9 poster flats, and other material documenting the company, including a catalog and photographs of its staff. It also includes a Geto Boys storyboard, made under the auspices of Rap-a-Lot Records, and two t-shirts.
Detailed List of Contents
- Digital Files
  Scope and Contents
  Some digital files can be viewed immediately in the UH Digital Library at http://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/pixel. Digital archival materials can also be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room by advance request. These materials may require up to one week to access. Contact curator Julie Grob (jgrob@uh.edu) for more information.
  - Digital Promotional Artwork
    The Digital Promotional Artwork series includes 40 digital files of artwork for CDs, vinyl records, videocassettes, and other promotional material produced by Pen & Pixel Graphics, Inc. The intended format for the promotional material files is indicated as part of the title for each item, but artwork was often reworked into various formats. For example, artwork created for a CD cover was often adapted for use in a poster. All but two of the digital files (Cher and Chris Rock) can be viewed immediately in the UH Digital Library at http://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/pixel. The digital files can also be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room by advance request. They may require up to one week to access. Contact curator Julie Grob (jgrob@uh.edu) for more information.
    - 2 Live Crew, The Real One, [Lil Joe Records], 12" record cover, 2010-017_00048.jpg, [1998] (Item 1)
    - B.G., Chopper City in the Ghetto, [Cash Money Records], CD cover, 2010-017_00006.jpg, [1999] (Item 2)
    - BHC, [Openin' Doors], [Big House Productions], CD cover, 2010-017_00007.jpg, [1997] (Item 3)
    - Big Ballers, [Simitar Ent.], videocassette cover, 2010-017_00008.jpg, [1998] (Item 4)
    - Big Bear, Doin Thangs, [Tru Game Records], postcard, 2010-017_00009.jpg, [1998] (Item 5)
    - Big Tymers, How You Luv That, Cash Money [Records], CD cover, 2010-017_00010.jpg, [1998] (Item 6)
    - Birdman, #1 Stunna, Cash Money [Records], CD cover, 2010-017_00011.jpg, [2002] (Item 7)
    - Cash Money Millionaires, Baller Blockin, [Polygram Video], videocassette cover, 2010-017_00005.jpg, [2000] (Item 8)
    - Cash Money Millionaires, logo, 2010-017_00012.jpg, undated (Item 9)
    - Cher, Live in Concert, HBO, poster, 2010-017_00013.jpg undated (Item 10)
    - Crazy, I Shed Tears for the World, [Ruff Era Records], audiocassette cover, 2010-017_00015.jpg, [1998] (Item 11)
    - Destiny's Child, Houston Livestock Show and Rodeo advertisement, poster, 2010-017_00017.jpg, 2002 (Item 12)
    - E-40, Tha Hall of Game, [Jive Records], CD cover and poster, 2010-017_00018.jpg, [1996] (Item 13)
    - Eightball & MJG, Comin' Out Hard, Suave Records, CD cover, 2010-017_00001.jpg, [1993] (Item 14)
    - Eightball & MJG, On the Outside Looking In, Suave [Records], CD cover, 2010-017_00002.jpg, [1994] (Item 15)
    - Eightball & MJG, On Top of the World, [Draper Inc.], CD cover, 2010-017_00031.jpg, [1995] (Item 16)
    - HBO, logo, 2010-017_00027.JPG, undated (Item 17)
    - J-Dawg, The Dawg House, [Big Boy Records], CD longbox cover, 2010-017_00022.jpg, [1997] (Item 18)
    - Juvenile, Back that Thang Up, [Cash Money/Universal?], CD longbox cover, 2010-017_00004.jpg, [2000?] (Item 19)
    - Juvenile, Project English, [Cash Money Records], CD cover, 2010-017_00023.jpg, [2001] (Item 20)
    - Leveraged Sellout, Damn, It Feels Good to be a Banker..., [Hyperion Books], book cover, 2010-017_00016.jpg, [2008] (Item 21)
    - Lil Menace, On Da Grind, CD cover, 2010-017_00025.jpg, undated (Item 22)
    - Lil Wayne, Lights Out, [Cash Money Records], CD cover, 2010-017_00026.jpg, [2000] (Item 23)
    - Master P, Animal Cruelty, book cover, 2010-017_00028.jpg, undated (Item 24)
    - [Master P], Ghetto Dope, [No Limit/Priority Records], CD cover, 2010-017_00028.jpg, [1997] (Item 25)
    - Master P, The Last Don [MP Da Last Don], [No Limit/Priority Records], CD cover, 2010-017_00030.jpg, [1998] (Item 26)
    - Mia X, Unlady Like, [Priority Records], CD cover, 2010-017_00046.jpg, undated (Item 27)
    - Mizery, Game Recognize Game, [Lewt Records], CD cover, 2010-017_00024.jpeg, undated (Item 28)
    - Mo B. Dick, Gangsta Harmony, [No Limit/Priority Records], CD cover, 2010-017_00029.jpg, [1999] (Item 29)
    - [Mystikal], Ghetto Fabulous, [Jive Records], CD cover, 2010-017_00020.jpg, [1998] (Item 30)
    - Pen & Pixel Graphics Inc., logo, 2010-017_00032.jpg, undated (Item 31)
    - Pen & Pixel Gloss N Floss, advertisement, 2010-017_00021.jpg, undated (Item 32)
    - PoBoy, CD cover, 2010-017_00041.jpg, undated (Item 33)
    - Rock, Chris, Bigger and Blacker, [Dreamworks], CD cover, 2010-017_00014.jpg, undated (Item 34)
    - Samm, Enemy of the Street, No Limit [Records], CD cover, 2010-017_00042.jpg, undated (Item 35)
    - Smartface Media Management, logo, 2010-017_00043.jpg, undated (Item 36)
    - South Park Mexican, Time is Money, [Umvd Labels], CD cover, 2010-017_00044.jpg, undated (Item 37)
    - The New No Limit Records, logo, 2010-017_00045.jpg, undated (Item 38)
    - Trinity Garden Cartel, Ghetto My Hood, [Cartel Records], CD cover, 2010-017_00033.jpg, undated (Item 39)
    - [VIBE magazine], postcard, 2010-017_00047.jpg, undated (Item 40)
  - Administrative Digital Files
    The Administrative Digital Files series includes 26 digital photographs taken at the Pen & Pixel Graphics, Inc. office and at a Pen & Pixel Graphics, Inc. 1998 staff event. The series also includes one speech by Shawn Brauch from 1999. All of the photographs can be viewed immediately in the UH Digital Library at http://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/pixel. These digital files can also be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room by advance request. They may require up to one week to access. Contact curator Julie Grob (jgrob@uh.edu) for more information.
    - Staff Photographs
      The staff photographs include 18 digital images of Pen & Pixel staff taken in 1998. They are available in the folder indicated below and include the filenames listed.
      - PPG [Pen & Pixel Graphics] Staff Photos, 2010-017_00049.jpg–2010-017_00066.jpg, December 28, 1998 (Folder 1)
    - Administrative Photographs
      - Pen & Pixel job project room, photograph, 2010-017_00034.jpg, undated (Item 1)
      - Pen & Pixel main client room desk, photograph, 2010-017_00035.jpg, undated (Item 2)
      - Pen & Pixel main creative lab room desk, photograph, 2010-017_00036.jpg, undated (Item 3)
      - Pen & Pixel main reception desk, photograph, 2010-017_00037.jpg, undated (Item 4)
      - Pen & Pixel number two client room desk, photograph, 2010-017_00038.jpg, undated (Item 5)
      - Pen & Pixel number three client room desk, photograph, 2010-017_00039.jpg, undated (Item 6)
      - Pen & Pixel photo studio, photograph, 2010-017_00040.jpg, undated (Item 7)
      - Pen & Pixel executives Shawn and Aaron Brauch, photograph, 2010-017_00003.jpg, undated (Item 8)
    - Speeches
      - Brauch, Shawn, The Future of Music in the Southwest speech for Urban Beat Magazine, 2010-017_00067.doc, 1999 (Item 1)
- Posters
  - A-G-2-A-Ke, Mil-Ticket, Rap-a-Lot Records, [1998] (Ovs box 1, Folder 1)
  - B.G., Chopper City, Cash Money Records, [1999] (Ovs box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bruno Cantu Jr., undated (Ovs box 1, Folder 3)
  - DJ Screw, 3 'N the Mornin', Bigtyme Records, [1995] (Ovs box 1, Folder 4)
  - DJ Screw, Sentimental Value, Wreckless Entertainment, [2002] (Ovs box 1, Folder 5)
  - E.S.G., Ocean of Funk, Perrion Records, [1994] (Ovs box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fade, It's in My Blood, Bad Young Brothers, undated (Ovs box 1, Folder 7)
  - Four U, I Wanna Bone, Sunny Boy Records, [1994?] (Ovs box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hollywood's Entertainment Exotic Entertainment, undated (Ovs box 1, Folder 9)
  - Pen & Pixel Graphics Image is Everything advertisement, 3 versions, undated (Ovs box 1, Folder 10)
  - South Park Mexican, Latin Throne, AV1 Productions, undated (Ovs box 1, Folder 11)
  - Supremacy Records, undated (Ovs box 1, Folder 12)
- Poster Flats
  - Poster Flats (Ovs box 1, Folder 13)
    - B.G., Chopper City in the Ghetto, Cash Money Records, [1999] (Ovs box 1, Folder 13, Item 1)
    - Big Tymers, I Got that Work, Cash Money Records, [2000] (Ovs box 1, Folder 13, Item 2)
    - Lil Milt, The Prophecy, East Wood Entertainment, [1997] (Ovs box 1, Folder 13, Item 3)
    - Lil Sin, Frustrated by Death, Blvd Records, [1996] (Ovs box 1, Folder 13, Item 4)
    - Playa G, U Not My Lady, East Wood Recordings, [1998] (Ovs box 1, Folder 13, Item 5)
    - Snoop Dogg, Da Game is to Be Sold, Not Told, No Limit Records, [1998] (Ovs box 1, Folder 13, Item 6)
- Promotional Material
  - Pen & Pixel Graphics
    - Pen & Pixel Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Pen & Pixel Graphics, Inc. catalog, undated (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 1)
      - [Pen & Pixel staff], photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 2)
      - Pen & Pixel Graphics Image is Everything advertisement, undated (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 3)
  - Artists
    - DJ Screw, Sentimental Value, Wreckless Entertainment, flyer, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Geto Boys, Rap-a-Lot Records, storyboard, 4 pages, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Got’ti, John, Cut Throat, Big Pocket Records, flyer, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Big Tymers, t-shirt, undated (Ovs box 2, Item 1)
    - Hot Boyz, t-shirt, undated (Ovs box 2, Item 2)